<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A preparation to the due consideration and reverent comming to the holy communion of the body and blood of our Lorde The contentes whereof followe in the next page.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1580</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 53 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09946</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20203</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106589</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842303</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842303</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6948</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09946)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6948)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 737:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A preparation to the due consideration and reverent comming to the holy communion of the body and blood of our Lorde The contentes whereof followe in the next page.</title>
                  <author>Barker, Christopher, 1529-1599.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[96] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Christopher Barker, printer to the Queenes most excellent Maiestie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1580.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: C. Barker.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-F.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Prayer-books and devotions --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6948:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6948:1"/>
            <p>A PREPARATION TO THE DVE CONSIDERATION <hi>AND REVERENT COM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to the holy Communion of the Body and Blood of our Lorde.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THE CONTENTES whereof followe in the next page.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>IMPRINTED AT LON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don by Chriſtopher Barker, Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <hi>ter to the Queenes moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Maieſtie.</hi> 1580.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:6948:2"/>
            <head>The Contents.</head>
            <list>
               <item>1 What an high dignitie it is to bee a Chriſtian, and partaker of the holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments of Chriſt.</item>
               <item>2 An inſtruction howe a Chriſtian ought to bee occupied, before he preſume to come to the Table of the Lord.</item>
               <item>3 Howe dangerous a thing it is to come vnworthily, or vnaduiſedly, to the holy Communion.</item>
               <item>4 A prayer to bee truely penitent for our ſinnes, before we receiue the holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of our Lord.</item>
               <item>5 A prayer to be ſayde immediatly before the receiuing of the holy Communion, and in the time of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> celebration therof.</item>
               <item>6 A thankeſgiuing after the receiuing of the holy Communion.</item>
               <item>7 An excellent Pſalme of King Dauid.</item>
               <item>8 A prayer for our Soueraigne Lady, Queene Elizabeth.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:6948:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the most excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent,</hi> vertuous, and our <hi>dread Soueraigne Lady Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth,</hi> Queene of England, France, <hi>and Ireland, &amp;c. Grace, mercie, and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting peace from God the Father, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lorde.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>AVING CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered,</hi> and called to memorie (moſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Soueraigne) the manifolde bleſſings and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites, giuen by the incomparable mercie of God to vs your ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, by your miniſterie, and the execution of your Kingly office, and vnder your Maieſties pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, and moſt peaceable go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement:
<pb facs="tcp:6948:3"/> wherein we doe not onely enioye, and quietly poſſeſſe the fruite of our labours, and all other our temporal commodities, but (that which is many thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d times more worth) euen the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie of conſcience, the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching and hearing of Gods moſt ſacred trueth, the fruition and vſe of the moſt holy Sacraments of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, which are ſeales vnto vs of the aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of our inheritance in the kingdome of GOD. And on the otherſide, hauing throughly weighed our contempt and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude to Almightie God, to his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt, and to
<pb facs="tcp:6948:3"/> your Maieſtie: by whom, as the onely meane from God, we reape all theſe good things, and are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended and mainteined in this our happie ſtate: I cannot inough wonder, nor ſufficiently lament, to ſee for the moſt part how litle we regarde, and how ſeldome we come to the hearing of Gods moſt holy worde, and to the cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration of theſe his moſt holy myſteries: and when we do come, howe rudely, vnaduiſedly, and vnreuerently it is, cannot be but moſt feareful, and moſt pitifull to beholde. Wherefore moſt graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Queene, and dread Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, the zeale and duetie I
<pb facs="tcp:6948:4"/> owe to the glory of GOD, and to the honour of your Maieſtie, (who cannot, but be greatly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honoured in this our negligence) hath enforced me to procure the ayde of an excellent learned and godly man, to compile three ſhort inſtructions, or admonitions vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the three firſt titles, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents in the ſeconde page of this litle manuel (whereunto are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded certaine moſt needefull prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and thankeſgiuing, all which may properly be entituled, <hi>A pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration to the holy Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the body and blood of our Lorde)</hi> to the ende wee may be moued with better conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:6948:4"/> of the benefits we receiue in theſe ſacred myſteries, and alſo with the greatneſſe of the danger for the abuſe and contempt of the ſame: Moſt humbly beſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching your Maieſtie, according to your accuſtomed goodneſſe, to accepte in good parte this my ſimple and vnſkilfull ſeruice, that by your good acceptation hereof, many of your Maieſties moſt honorable houſholde, and others alſo, may be drawen and procured to the exerciſe of the ſame, to their further inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, comfort, and conſolation, by the working of Gods holy Spirit: to whom with the Father &amp; the
<pb facs="tcp:6948:5"/> Sonne, be all glory for euer, and to your Maieſtie, a moſt honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, long and prosperous raigne ouer vs, with all other his merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full bleſſings in this life, and in the life to come, ioy, felicitie, and continuall dwelling with all the bleſſed Angels and Saints in the kingdome of God, world without ende, AMEN.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Maieſties moſt lowly ſubiect, and ſeruant, C. Barker.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:6948:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>What a high digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie</hi> it is to be a Chriſtian, <hi>and partaker of the</hi> holy Sacraments of Chriſt.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>SAINT IOHN</hi> the Euangeliſt, in the firſt Chapter of his Goſpel writeth, that our Sauiour Chriſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming into the worlde, which was made by him, was vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowen of it: yea, comming among his owne, of his owne was not receiued: but yet to as many as receiued him, he gaue this dignitie, that they ſhould be called the ſonnes of
<pb facs="tcp:6948:6"/> God, which are borne not of fleſh, nor of blood, nor of the will of man, but of God. By which teſtimonie of the holy Ghoſt, wee may vnderſtande howe great and excellent is the dignitie of true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans: namely, that they be the children of God, begotten not carnally, but ſpiritually of God himſelfe. And that we ſhould not deceiue our ſelues, by a falſe imagination of chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, as it is commonly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and reputed in the blinde world, the ſame ſcripture tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth vs who be true Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in deede: not euery one that
<pb facs="tcp:6948:6"/> is ſo called, or would be ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted, not euery one which hath taken vpon him the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſigne and badge of chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianitie, which is the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Baptiſme: but onely thoſe which receiue Chriſt, are true Chriſtians, and the children of God. But who are they that haue receiued Chriſt, that they may be partakers of ſo high a dignitie? euen they which ſeeing, acknowledging and confeſſing their owne ſhameful, miſerable, and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable eſtate, which they haue not onely receiued by propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation from their parents, but
<pb facs="tcp:6948:7"/> alſo haue wilfullye incurred through the iuſt iudgement of God for their owne ſinnes, do willingly, ioyfully, and thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully heare &amp; obey this voyce of our Sauiour Chriſt, Mat. 11. and 28. <hi>Come vnto mee all ye that labour, and be heauy laden, and I will refreſh you.</hi> And ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing their whole truſt and confidence in the mercie of God (whoſe iuſtice they know to be ſatiſfied in the merites and ſufferings of his onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten ſonne our Lorde and Sauiour Chriſt, their whole and onely Redeemer) doe willingly take vpon them the
<pb facs="tcp:6948:7"/> ſweete &amp; eaſie yoke of Chriſt, which he requireth in the next verſe to bee taken of all them that come vnto him, &amp; looke to be refreſhed by him: which yoke of obedience vnto the rule of Chriſt, though it ſeeme harde and vnpleaſant to bee borne, vnto the corrupt nature of man, yet vnto the children of God, (whoſe weakenes is aſsiſted by the holy Ghoſt, &amp; their faults co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted of weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, are waſhed away with the blood of Chriſt) there is nothing more ſweete, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, and delectable: inſomuch that Dauid vpon this conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,
<pb facs="tcp:6948:8"/> preferreth the Lawe of God before hony, and the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny combe in ſweeteneſſe, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſting that it is more to bee deſired then all iewels of gold and precious ſtones. Beholde, theſe are true Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s which haue receiued Chriſt by faith, and gladly bring out the fruits of faith in all godlineſſe of life, to the glory of God their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the profite of Gods children, their brethren and ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters. Therefore if we be ſuch, whatſoeuer we be in the eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the worlde, wee are moſt honourable. And if wee haue all the vaine titles of
<pb facs="tcp:6948:8"/> worldly honour heaped vpon vs, &amp; be not ſuch, we are moſt vile and contemptible in the ſight of God: for God maketh more accompt of his children, then of all the creatures of the worlde beſide: as euery father more eſteemeth his naturall ſonnes and daughters, then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other thing hee hath in the world. yea for them the world was made, for them the ſonne of God became man, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered death for their redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: for them the worlde is continued, that their full nom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber out of all ages might bee gathered, in which God hath
<pb facs="tcp:6948:9"/> appointed them to liue: and when the nomber of them is once accompliſhed and fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, this worlde ſhalbe at an ende, and Chriſt ſhall come to giue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all together that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect rewarde, which God hath promiſed, &amp; he for them hath deſerued. What worldly dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, haue it neuer ſo ſwelling titles of honour and glory, can be comparable to this high dignitie of true Chriſtians? If we ſhould ſpeake of the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes of Knights, Lordes, Earles, Dukes, &amp;c. they are all ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted and excelled by the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Kings &amp; Emperors:
<pb facs="tcp:6948:9"/> and for what cauſe, but that the maieſtie of Kings and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours ſo farre paſſeth thoſe meaner titles of honor before rehearſed? It followeth then of neceſſitie, that the more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent the parents are, the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is the dignitie of the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: and conſequently, by howe much the eternall glory and maieſtie of God excelleth the honor &amp; dignitie of earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Kinges and Emperours, by ſo much the dignitie and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of Gods children excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the honour and dignitie of Kings and Emperours chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. Wherefore, if in reſpect
<pb facs="tcp:6948:10"/> of worldly honor, we worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eſteeme thoſe happy, which haue bin borne of earthly prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: much more ought we to accompt them bleſſed in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly &amp; ſpirituall dignitie, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whom this prerogatiue is graunted, that they ſhould be called the ſonnes of God. For thereby they are aſſured, not onely to bee mainteined and protected by the gouernour of all things in heauen and earth, but alſo they are certainly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to receiue ſuch an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, as it is meete for the Almightie creator of al things to beſtowe vpon them, whom
<pb facs="tcp:6948:10"/> he accepteth &amp; taketh for his welbeloued children: yea, ſuch is his bountifull goodneſſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes vs his adopted ſonnes and daughters, that as his cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen veſſels, S. Paul doeth teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, he hath made vs aſſurance, and by the earneſt of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit, put vs in poſſeſſion, (though not yet in full fruitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) of that moſt roial inheritance, which he giueth to his onely naturall ſonne, our Lorde and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt. Rom. 8. And as the Spirit of adoption, by which we crie, <hi>Abba,</hi> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which is the Spirite of trueth, and therefore can not
<pb facs="tcp:6948:11"/> deceiue vs, beareth witnes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly to our ſpirits, that we are the ſonnes of God: So it hath pleaſed our heauenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, outwardly by holy ſignes and Sacraments, to teſtifie the ſame vnto vs: which Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as ſeales of his promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes which are dayly preached vnto vs out of his holy worde, he hath giuen for a further and more full confirmation and ſtrengthening of our faith, and moſt perfect aſſura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of thoſe things which hee hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: by which Sacraments al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo he doeth not onely ſignifie and ſhewe what he hath pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed
<pb facs="tcp:6948:11"/> to doe for vs, but alſo worketh effectually in thoſe that bee his true children, the ſame thinges which he doeth ſignifie and teache by them. For as by his holy worde hee teacheth vs, that after he is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled with vs for Chriſt his ſake, hee accepteth vs for his deare children, and aſſureth vs that he will neuer forſake vs, but continue his mercie and loue towardes vs for euer and euer: euen ſo he teſtifieth and ratifieth the ſame by his holy Sacraments. For in as much as it is neceſſary, that if we be the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God, we muſt know
<pb facs="tcp:6948:12"/> that wee are borne of God, it hath pleaſed him in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Baptiſme, which is the lauer of regeneration or newe birth, to teſtifie vnto vs, that by vertue of the blood of Chriſt waſhing away our ſinnes, as water doeth the vncleanneſſe of our bodies, &amp; by the grace of his holy Spirite working wonderfully in our ſoules, our olde man is aboliſhed, and we borne anewe of water and of the holy Ghoſt, to be the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God. Being thus aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of our ſpirituall birth, that we ſhoulde not doubt of our euerlaſting preſeruation in the
<pb facs="tcp:6948:12"/> ſame ſtate of Gods deare chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, hee hath prepared vs al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo a ſpirituall nouriſhment of meate and drinke, by which we ſhould be fedde to euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting life: namely, the fleſh &amp; blood of Ieſus Chriſt, which was broken and ſhedde for vs vpon the croſſe, that it might be ſpirituall foode to all them that ſhalbe partakers of it by faith. Of which euerlaſting foode and nouriſhment, hee hath giuen vs a ſeale or ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in his holy Supper, that, receiuing that bread and cup of the Lorde worthily, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his holy inſtitution, we
<pb facs="tcp:6948:13"/> ſhoulde no more doubt that our ſoules are ſpiritually fedde and nouriſhed with the preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous body and blood of Chriſt, to the forgiuenes of our ſinnes and life euerlaſting, then wee doubt that the outwarde ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which wee haue taken into our bodies, according to their quantitie doe feede and nouriſh the ſame, vnto the maintenance of this temporal life. Whereby wee may eaſely ſee vnto howe great honour wee are called of our Sauiour Chriſt, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we are made par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of that moſt holy and heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly Table, wherein he ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth
<pb facs="tcp:6948:13"/> forth vnto vs, moſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy wretches of our ſelues to ſitte at his high Table, no meaner foode then his owne fleſh &amp; blood, to be a ſpirituall nouriſhment vnto our ſoules, whereby wee are made one body with him, and members one of an other, and an holy temple of GOD, through the Spirite of Chriſt dwelling in vs, and Kinges and Prieſtes do reigne with him, and praiſe his holy name for euermore.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:6948:14"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <hi>An inſtruction</hi> how a Chriſtian ought to <hi>be occupied, before he</hi> preſume to come to the Table of the Lord.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>SALOMON, in the</hi> 23 Chapter of his Prouerbs, exhorteth them which ſhalbe partakers of an earthly princes table, to haue due conſideration of their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour thereat to be vſed, and of ſuch meates as ſhalbe ſet before them: how much more ought a Chriſtian diligently to weigh with him ſelfe when he is called vnto the high Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the Lord, by whom hee
<pb facs="tcp:6948:14"/> is called, whither he is called, vnto what he is called, and for what end he is called. Verely, a Chriſtian man, when hee is bidden to this royall banket, is called by no perſon of meane eſtate in this life, nor by any of the higheſt dignitie in this worlde, but by him that made them all: and in compariſon of whoſe excellencie they all are but duſt and aſhes. It is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the Lord our GOD, the creator &amp; maker of all things, moſt holy, moſt righteous, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and abhorring all ſinne and wickednes, in whoſe ſight no vncleane or filthie perſon
<pb facs="tcp:6948:15"/> may abide to ſtand: but ſuch as are holy, righteous, cleane, and pure in heart, are acceptable before him. The place where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto a Chriſtian man is called, when he is required to be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of the holy Sacrament, is the Lordes Table, whereof this earthly &amp; corruptible ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble is but a figure &amp; ſhadowe: for euen as he that calleth vs, which is God our Father, and that whereunto we are called, which is the body and blood of Chriſt, is in heauen at the right hand of God in glory &amp; maieſtie: eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo the Lords Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, on which we ſhall be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers
<pb facs="tcp:6948:15"/> of the ſame, is lifted vp aboue all height of the viſible skies, into that place of Gods eternall glory, and maieſtie, where Ieſus Chriſt is reſident in the throne of his magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence. The holy feaſt &amp; ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet, whereunto a Chriſtian man is called, conſiſteth not of earthly dainties prepared by the arte of man, to pleaſe the bodily taſte, which as ſoone as they are receiued into the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, tende to putrifaction and corruption: but of that liuely bread which came downe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heauen, and giueth life to the world, euen the fleſh &amp; blood
<pb facs="tcp:6948:16"/> of our Sauiour Chriſt, the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maculat lambe of God, which gaue himſelfe an holy and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defiled ſacrifice vnto God his Father once for all, and found thereby euerlaſting redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: of which moſt holy and heauenly meate and drinke, whoſoeuer is partaker, ſhall liue for euer. The ende where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a Chriſtian man is called to be partaker of this holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, is, that hee might be aſſured, that hee is regenerate and borne againe by the holy Ghoſt, to be the child of God, and inheriter of the kingdom of heauen, notwithſtanding
<pb facs="tcp:6948:16"/> that hee remaineth ſtill as yet ſubiect vnto death of his body, and (that which is more to be feared) through infirmitie fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth often times into ſinne, the reward whereof by the iuſtice of God, is death both of body and ſoule: yet being nouriſhed and fedde with the foode of immortalitie and euerlaſting life, which is the fleſh &amp; blood of our Sauiour Chriſt (as hee him ſelfe teſtifyeth in the ſixt Chapter of Iohn) hee ſhall by the diuine vertue and quicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſpirite of our Sauiour Chriſt, be rayſed vp in the laſt day vnto euerlaſting felicitie.
<pb facs="tcp:6948:17"/> Theſe thinges if a Chriſtian man doe duely conſider, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee preſume to come to the Lordes Table, he will not thruſt forwarde himſelfe raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, vnaduiſedly, &amp; contemptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, but with ſuch reuerence, preparation, and examination, as is meete for him that is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by ſo great a perſon vnto ſo high a place, to be partaker of ſo holy, and ſo fearefull my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, for ſo waighty and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie an ende and purpoſe. For in reſpect of him that cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, which is moſt holy and righteous, he will remember, that it is his part to cleanſe his
<pb facs="tcp:6948:17"/> ſoule from all vncleanneſſe of ſinne and wickedneſſe, by true and hearty repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tance: he dare not appeare in his preſence, (which ſeeth and knoweth the ſecrets of his heart) with an outward ſhewe of fained ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe and counterfet ſorow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe for his ſinnes, which he purpoſeth not to leaue and forſake, but to continue in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, after the receite of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and to delight in them as much as euer he did before. He will not preſume to deride and mocke the Iudge of al the worlde, with a faigned coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of modeſtie, taken vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:6948:18"/> him for a few houres while he is in the Church, and laide aſide againe almoſt aſſone as he ſteppeth ouer the threſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde of the Church doore, to returne no leſſe to his former lightnes, vanitie, pride, luſt, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſneſſe and other vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines, then to his priuate houſe and lodging. And when hee conſidereth that hee is called into heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, where no vnclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe or corruption can abide, where holineſſe &amp; righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe doth dwel, he will call to mind the anſwere which God maketh to Dauid in the 15. Pſalme, where hee inquireth
<pb facs="tcp:6948:18"/> who ſhall dwell in his Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle, and reſt in his holy hill: Euen hee that leadeth an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corrupt life without hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, without fraude and guile, couetouſnes or oppreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that dealeth iuſtly, faithfully, and mercifully with all men: ſuch a one ſhall neuer be remoued. Hee that is called into heauen, where Chriſt is ſitting at the right hand of GOD, and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly obeyeth his calling, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowlegeth that he muſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the earth, with all earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affections, and ſet his minde vpon heauenly thinges, vpon thoſe thinges that are aboue,
<pb facs="tcp:6948:19"/> and not vpon the earth, as S. Paul exhorteth, Coloſſians the 3. Chap. hee muſt mortifie his me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers that are on earth, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, and all vncleanneſſe, couetouſneſſe, and deceitful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, wrath, malice, blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, and filthie ſpeaking: and putting off the olde man with his workes, he muſt put on the newe man, which is renewed according to the image of him that created him, in holineſſe and righteouſneſſe, in merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, humilitie, meekeneſſe, long ſuffering, and forgiuenes of all them that haue offended vs, euen as God hath forgiuen
<pb facs="tcp:6948:19"/> vs in Chriſt Ieſus. And for as much as the diſtance betwene the earth, where we are ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and the Heauen, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto wee are called, as to the place of our inheritance, is ſo great, that it is not poſſible for our heauy &amp; lumpiſh bodies to aſcende thither, before they be made conformable &amp; like to the glorious bodie of our Sauiour Chriſt, which is gone thither before vs to prepare a place: a Chriſtian man will conſider, that as yet he can no otherwiſe bee lifted vp into heauen, but in heart and ſoule, by the winges of faith. And
<pb facs="tcp:6948:20"/> therefore he wil ſeeke to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme and ſtrengthen his faith, by the often and diligent me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation of the moſt comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble promiſes of God contei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the holy Scriptures, and by earneſt and feruent prayer vnto God for Chriſt his ſake, to increaſe his faith by the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of his holy Spirit, as well in this time of his participation of the heauenly myſteries, as at all other times, vnto the ende of his life. Yea, that ſpirituall foode of the body &amp; blood of Chriſt, whereof he is called to be a partaker, wil admoniſh &amp; put a Chriſtian man in minde,
<pb facs="tcp:6948:20"/> as well of repentance, purpoſe of ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dment, reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie, with which hee ought to bee prepared that ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the Sacrament worthily: as alſo, that faith and conſtant beliefe in the promiſes of God is neceſſarily required of him that ſhalbe nouriſhed with ſo wonderfull &amp; heauenly foode. For were it not that the ſonne of God, which is trueth it ſelfe, hath promiſed by his holye worde, to giue vs his body and blood to bee meate in deede, and drinke in deede, to feede vs vnto euerlaſting life: and for aſſurance of this his promiſe,
<pb facs="tcp:6948:21"/> doth giue vs his ſeale in bread and wine, which therefore hee calleth by the name of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and blood, becauſe they do truely, and not vainely repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent vnto vs the trueth of his promiſe, and effectuall perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of the ſame: howe ſhould we differ from the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleuing Iewes, which vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding carnally, that which our Sauiour Chriſt ſpake ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually, demaunded howe it were poſſible to giue his fleſh to be eaten, and his blood to be drunken? But being inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by faith, although the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie farre paſſe the reache of
<pb facs="tcp:6948:21"/> any mans vnderſtanding, yet doe we nothing doubt, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his holy word and promiſe, after a heauenly and ſpiritual maner, he giueth to al them that are worthily parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of that holy Sacrament, his very body and blood to be ſpirituall meate and drinke, whereby they are fed &amp; nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed vnto that life which is immortall and incorruptible. Which faith of ours receiueth ſtrength and increaſe by wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie participation of this holy myſterie: for which ende and purpoſe it was inſtituted and ordeined to our comfort. In
<pb facs="tcp:6948:22"/> conſideration whereof, and of all &amp; euery the reſpects before mentioned, a Chriſtian man is compelled to fall down be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the throne of Gods grace, and from the bottome of his heart to yeelde moſt humble and vnfeigned thanks to God the Father, with the ſonne our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, &amp; the holy Ghoſt, by whoſe infinit mercy and goodneſſe, without al me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite and deſert of himſelfe, hee is called to ſo high honor and dignitie, that he is admitted to be a gheſt at the Lords Table, in which hee is made partaker of the fleſh and blood of the
<pb facs="tcp:6948:22"/> ſonne of GOD, who ſo loued the worlde, that hee gaue his only begotten ſonne, to ſuffer moſt cruell &amp; ſhamefull death for the redemption of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde, to ſatiſfie the wrath of God, &amp; to reconcile vs againe into his fauour, of his enimies to make vs his children, and of his children to make vs ioynt heyres with his onely begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſonne Ieſus Chriſt our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour. Laſt of all, a Chriſtian man thus aſſured, that hee is made partaker of the body &amp; blood of Chriſt his head, of whom hee is nowe made a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing member, muſt acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb facs="tcp:6948:23"/> &amp; purpoſe with himſelf, that it is his bound duetie, not onely to be more circumſpect &amp; watchful of himſelfe, that he bee not forgetfull for ſo high and incomparable a benefite, nor vnthankfull to ſo mercifull a Lord that hath thus loued &amp; ſaued him: But alſo to ſhewe all loue &amp; tender affection to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes all them, which by the ſame meanes are made fellow me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers with him of the ſame myſticall body: and as occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and abilitie ſhall ſerue, like a liuing member, to feele ioye and comfort at the proſperitie of his fellowe members, and
<pb facs="tcp:6948:23"/> to be ſo grieued at the hurt or affliction of any of them, that he be redie to relicue &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort them, to ayde and aſſiſt them, as we ſee by the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the members and partes of our naturall bodye. Hee therefore that examineth him ſelfe after theſe rules, ſhall be rightly prepared to receiue the Sacrament worthily, to his euerlaſting comfort.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:6948:24"/>
            <head>¶ <hi>Howe dangerous</hi> a thing it is to come vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <hi>thily or vnaduiſedly, to the holy Communion.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Nworthily they come</hi> to the holy Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, not whoſoeuer are vnworthy of that high honour, which GOD vouchſafeth them whom hee calleth to his holy Table: (for then ſhould all men, euen the moſt righteous come vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily. For no man is worthy to ſtand in the Lordes preſence, much leſſe to ſitte as a bidden gheſte at the mariage of his Sonne, or rather as a childe, at
<pb facs="tcp:6948:24"/> the high Table of Almightie God the Father, but that hee of his infinite mercie, whereby hee accepteth them to bee his children, vouchſafeth alſo to giue them this heauenly nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment.) But all they come vnworthily, not onely which come like hypocrites, with fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned hearts and contemptuous mindes againſt the Lord, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they pretende to worſhip: but alſo euen as many as preſume raſhly, negligently, and vnad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſedly to receiue the holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament without due exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of themſelues, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of the excellent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite
<pb facs="tcp:6948:25"/> whereof they come to be partakers. Of them S. Paul writeth, that they eate and drinke, not the body of Chriſt, whom they deſpiſe in his holy myſteries, but their own dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, becauſe they diſcerne not the Lordes body, from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bodily meates &amp; drinkes: For ſeeing our Sauiour Chriſt hath adorned theſe holy my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries with the name of his moſt precious body &amp; blood; whoſoeuer conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>neth or light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly regardeth the fame, muſt needes deſerue ſuch puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and condemnation, as they which abuſe not only the
<pb facs="tcp:6948:25"/> name of GOD, (of whom hee proteſteth that he wil not hold the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> guiltles:) but alſo the ſeale of God, whereby hee offereth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aſſurance of their redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and euen the very bodie and blood of Chriſt, whereof this Sacrament is a true and liuely repreſentation. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Apoſtle ſayth, Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer eateth this Bread, and drinketh of this Cuppe of the Lord vnworthily, ſhall not be guiltie of abuſing of bread and wine, and other ſuch like crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, (the abuſing whereof is neuertheleſſe vnanſwerable before GOD:) but he ſhalbe
<pb facs="tcp:6948:26"/> guiltie of the body and blood of Chriſt. Which ſinne, howe horrible and gricuous it is in the ſight of God, to be guiltie of the body &amp; blood of Chriſt, we may eaſely perceiue, if we call to remembrance the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of thoſe, who moſte cruelly and deſpitefully betrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, condemned, ſcourged, and crucified his moſt holy and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent bodie, when hee li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued vpon the earth. The guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſe of whoſe treaſon, falſe witneſſing, vniuſt conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning, cruel ſcourging, and crowning with thornes, &amp; moſt diſpite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full crucifiyng, and ſhedding
<pb facs="tcp:6948:26"/> of his moſt precious blood, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide ſpitting, ſcorning, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiling: the guiltineſſe (I ſay) of all which iniuries and ville<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies they do moſt iuſtly heape vpon themſelues, which vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily, vnaduiſedly, raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or negligently preſume to come to the Lords Table, and ſo become guiltie of the body &amp; blood of our Sauiour Chriſt: whereby they procure vnto themſelues (if GOD ſhould deale with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in iuſtice) ſuch puniſhment, as was deſerued by <hi>Iudas Iſcarioth,</hi> the falſe ſuborned witneſſes, <hi>Annas</hi> and <hi>Caiaphas,</hi> with the reſt of the
<pb facs="tcp:6948:27"/> high Prieſtes and Phariſes, <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late</hi> with his ſouldiers, and the people that cryed out vpon him, Crucifie him, Crucifie him. And more worthily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue they ſuch puniſhment, then many of theſe before named: for of them the holy Ghoſt teſtifieth, that they did it ignorantly: for if they had knowen him, they would not haue crucified the Lord of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. But theſe men contemne and deſpiſe him, whom they knowe and confeſſe to be the Lord of glory, and the eternal Sonne of God: the other deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſed him in the eſtate of his
<pb facs="tcp:6948:27"/> humilitie, when his Godhead was couered with the ſhape of a ſeruant: but theſe men ſet light by him, and contemne him, nowe hee ſitteth in his throne of magnificence and maieſtie. Therfore, much grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is their guiltineſſe, &amp; more grieuous is their condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, if the Lorde ſhoulde deale with them according to their deſertes. But although hee be ready to pardon and forgiue ſuch as haue ſo deſpiſed him, vpon their heartie and earneſt repentance, euen as hee was ready to pardon them which crucified him: yet doth he not
<pb facs="tcp:6948:28"/> ſuffer his children to bee alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether without chaſtiſement, but that they may more deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſider howe grieuouſly they haue treſpaſſed againſt him, hee puniſheth them of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes with ſharpe ſicknes and ſudden death, which haue preſumed vnworthily to bee partakers of his holy myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, euen as the Apoſtle ſaith: For this cauſe many among you are ſicke, and ſome are fallen aſleepe, by which tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall puniſhments, if the reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due can beware, and learne to iudge themſelues, they ſhall eſcape the iudgement of God:
<pb facs="tcp:6948:28"/> but if neither by Gods threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, nor example of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, they will be taught to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend this great &amp; groſſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of Gods lenitie &amp; mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, they ſhall heape vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues vengeance in the day of wrath: from which, our moſt mercifull GOD for Chriſt his ſake, vouchſafe to deliuer vs.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:6948:29"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <hi>A prayer to be</hi> truely penitent for our ſins, <hi>before wee receiue the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the Lord.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Eternall, and moſt mercifull Father, we moſt vile and wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched ſinners (and yet thy children through thy ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular grace and mercie) fall downe before thee, moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly acknowledging and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing our owne vileneſſe and vnworthineſſe, through our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite ſinnes and wickedneſſe, to come into the preſence of thy maieſtie, or ſtande before thy face, whom wee haue ſo
<pb facs="tcp:6948:29"/> grieuouſly offended, &amp; diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured thy glorious name, by which we are called. O Lord, we are aſhamed to preſent our ſelues into thy ſight, who ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt and knoweſt all our wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, much more clearely then wee our ſelues, and yet ſuch is our miſerable eſtate, that when wee looke backe to our former life that is paſt, we ſee nothing in a maner, but a monſtrous heape of ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, error, ſinne, wickedneſſe, and vngodlineſſe: for which, O Lorde GOD, we are ſo farre off from making any ſatiſfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction or amendes, that we are
<pb facs="tcp:6948:30"/> not ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly diſpleaſed with our ſelues for ſo great vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe, nor ſorowfull inough for ſo great wickedneſſe. Therefore moſt mercifull Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, wee flie vnto thy onely grace, and bountifull mercie, which art the onely fountaine of all good giftes: moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beſeeching thee to molli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie our ſtony heartes with the deawe of thy holy Spirite, to ſubdue the pride of our nature with the terror of thy iuſtice, to graunt vs true repentance, that we may be truely turned vnto thee. Conuert vs, O Lorde God, &amp; then ſhall we be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted:
<pb facs="tcp:6948:30"/> yea, turne vnto vs the light of thy countenance, and then ſhall wee bee ſaued. And for as much as thou haſt giuen the holy Sacrament of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and blood of thy ſonne our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, to bee a ſeale of thy promiſed mercies and our redemption, to bee a confirmation of our faith, and medicine of our infirmitie: we heartily beſeeche thee, moſt mercifull Father, that as wee humbly preſent our ſelues to celebrate this thy holy inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, not in preſumption of our worthines, but imboldned by thy heauenly voyce comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="tcp:6948:31"/> vs: ſo wee may be parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of thy holy myſteries to our comfort, that we may feele the fruite and effect ofthy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe adioined vnto them, liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly working in vs. Preuent by thy grace (O Lorde God) leaſt through our negligence &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault, the ſame bee not onely made vnfruitfull vnto vs, but alſo hurtfull, which thou haſt ordeined and graciouſly gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen for our profite and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort: but graunt that thy grace and goodnes aſſiſting vs in all things, wee may enioy thy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites to thy glory, and our euerlaſting felicitie, through
<pb facs="tcp:6948:31"/> our Lorde and onely Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt: to whom with thee and the holy Ghoſt, bee all glory, praiſe and domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, both nowe and for euer, AMEN.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>
               <hi>A praier to be ſaid</hi> immediatly before the <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing of the holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, in the time of the celebration thereof.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>O Moſt gratious &amp; boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull Sauiour of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde, Ieſu Chriſt our onely redeemer, which for our ſake diddeſt abaſe thy
<pb facs="tcp:6948:32"/> ſelfe to come downe from thy eternall throne of Maieſtie, in which thou art equall with God the Father and the holy Ghoſt, to take vpon thee the ſhape of a ſeruant, that thou mighteſt be ſtricke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God the Father for our ſinnes, and buf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feted for our iniquities, that through thy ſtripes we might be healed, which diddeſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come obedient (to ſatiſfie for our diſobedience) vnto the moſt ſhameful &amp; curſed death of the croſſe, that thy ſhame might be our glory, thy curſe our bleſſing, and thy death our life euerlaſting: We moſt
<pb facs="tcp:6948:32"/> humbly beſeeche thee, that as we preſent our ſelues at thy holy Table, to celebrate an holy memoriall of theſe thine ineſtimable benefites, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to thy gratious inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and ordinance: ſo it may pleaſe thee, all lettes and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derances, which our vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe may obiect before thy righteouſneſſe, being taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way through thy onely good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, wee may receiue to our comfort, that which thou of thy mercie doeſt offer vnto vs: euen thy moſt precious body and blood, to bee a ſpirituall foode and nouriſhment, to
<pb facs="tcp:6948:33"/> feede vs vnto immortalitie both of body and ſoule, that we may glorifie thee with the Father and the holy Ghoſt, one eternall God world with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ende, Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>
               <hi>A thankeſgiuing</hi> after the receiuing of the <hi>holy Communion.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>O Almightie and moſt mercifull Father, what thankes are we able to yeelde vnto thee, ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient for ſo many and ſo great benefites, of which wee are
<pb facs="tcp:6948:33"/> dayly partakers, without all merite or deſert of ours, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough thy onely goodnes and mercie? And nowe (O Lorde God) that thou haſt refreſhed our ſoules with the heauenly foode of the body and blood of our Sauiour Chriſt, in this holy myſterie and Sacrament of thine inſtitution, whereby wee call to remembrance our whole and perfect redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by the bitter paſſion and ſhedding of the blood of thy immaculate lambe, our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Ieſus Chriſt, who offered himſelfe to bee a ſacrifice of ſweete ſauour and full recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation
<pb facs="tcp:6948:34"/> once for all to thy Maieſtie for our ſinnes: howe are wee able to teſtifie our thankfulneſſe for ſo wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full mercie and goodnes? The conſideration of the greatnes whereof, ſwalloweth vp all our cogitations and thoughts: ſo that wee finde nothing but eternall and infinite prayſe to be due vnto thee, for ſo infinite and eternall mercie. Which, becauſe (O Lord) wee are nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther able, nor worthie to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe and ſet foorth, we hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beſeeche thee, as well for this want and imperfection, as for all other our weakenes and
<pb facs="tcp:6948:34"/> vnſufficiencie, to accept the ſatiſfaction of our Lorde and Redeemer Ieſus Chriſt, who hath waſhed vs, and made vs Kinges and Prieſtes, to offer vp ſpirituall ſacrifice of prayſe and thankeſgiuing acceptable vnto thee. In whom (O Lord) we yeeld vnto thee, that which we cannot of our ſelues, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall and worthie thankes, honour and glory, worlde without ende, AMEN.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:6948:35"/>
            <head>
               <hi>An excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Pſalme</hi> of King Dauid.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y ſoule, prayſe thou the Lorde, &amp; all that is within mee, prayſe his holy Name.</p>
            <p>2 My ſoule, prayſe thou the Lorde, and forget not all his benefites.</p>
            <p>3 Which forgiueth all thine iniquitie, and healeth all thine infirmities.</p>
            <p>4 Which redeemeth thy life from the graue, and crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth thee with mercie and compaſſions.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:6948:35"/>
            <p>5 Which ſatiſfieth thy mouth with good thinges: and thy youth is renued like the egles.</p>
            <p>6 The Lord executeth righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe and iudgement to all that are oppreſſed.</p>
            <p>7 Hee made his wayes kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen vnto Moſes, &amp; his workes vnto the children of Iſrael.</p>
            <p>8 The Lorde is full of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion and mercie, ſlowe to anger, and of great kinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>9 Hee will not alway chide, neither keepe his anger for euer.</p>
            <p>10 Hee hath not dealt with vs after our ſinnes, nor rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb facs="tcp:6948:36"/> vs according to our ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities.</p>
            <p>11 For as high as the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen is aboue the earth, ſo great is his mercie towarde them that feare him.</p>
            <p>12 As farre as the Eaſt is from the Weſt, ſo farre hath he remooued our ſinnes from vs.</p>
            <p>13 As a father hath compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion on his children, ſo hath the Lord compaſſion on them that feare him.</p>
            <p>14 For he knoweth where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of wee be made: hee remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breth that wee are but duſt.</p>
            <p>15 The dayes of man are as
<pb facs="tcp:6948:36"/> graſſe: as a flower of the field, ſo floriſheth hee.</p>
            <p>16 For the winde goeth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it, and it is gone, and the place thereof ſhall knowe it no more.</p>
            <p>17 But the louing kindneſſe of the Lord endureth for euer and euer vpon them that feare him, and his righteouſneſſe vpon childrens children,</p>
            <p>18 Vnto them that keepe his couenant, and thinke vpon his commaundements to doe them.</p>
            <p>19 The Lord hath prepared his throne in heauen, and his kingdome ruleth ouer all.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:6948:37"/>
            <p>20 Praiſe the Lorde, ye his Angels, that excell in ſtrength, that doe his commandement in obeying the voyce of his worde.</p>
            <p>21 Praiſe the Lorde, all ye his hoſtes, ye his ſeruants that doe his pleaſure.</p>
            <p>22 Praiſe the Lorde, all ye his workes, in all places of his dominion: my ſoule, prayſe thou the Lord.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:6948:37"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A prayer for our</hi> moſt gratious Soueraigne <hi>Lady, Queene Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Almightie eternall God, Creator, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour, and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of all thinges, Lorde of all lordes, and King of all kings, who madeſt man like vnto thine owne image, that he ſhoulde honour, ſerue, and obey thee onely, and that all other thy creatures ſhoulde ſerue to his vſe and commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie, ouer whom thou madeſt him lorde and ruler, the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden
<pb facs="tcp:6948:38"/> fruite only except: but hee moſt miſerable man, by his owne diſobedience in ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thereof, loſt not only that kingly prerogatiue, but broght himſelfe, and all his poſteritie, into the ſtate of eternall dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. Yet thou (O Lord) in thine vnſpeakable mercy didſt then promiſe, and in time broughteſt to paſſe, that thine onely ſonne became man like vnto vs, ſinne except, and was borne of a pure virgine by thy diuine prouidence and power: who to reſtore this, now, moſt miſerable man, with all vs, whoſe children by nature wee
<pb facs="tcp:6948:38"/> are, vnto the ſtate of eternall ſaluation, did ſuffer moſte ſhameful, moſt vile and bitter, yea moſt cruel &amp; painful death on the croſſe, whereon his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious body was broken, and his precious blood ſhed, a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient ranſome, a ful ſatiſfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and iuſt recompence of thy iuſtice and lawe, for all them that beleeue and embrace thy Goſpel and ſacred trueth. But, O Lorde our good God, bee mercifull vnto vs, who by our infirmitie (through the fall of this lordely man, our greate grandfather Adam) can not now liue in any peaceable or
<pb facs="tcp:6948:39"/> good condition &amp; ſtate, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out magiſtrates and kinges to rule and gouerne vs: we there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore moſt humbly and hearti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beſeeche thy diuine Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, for the loue of thine onely ſonne Ieſus Chriſt, to looke downe with thy fatherly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion vpon thy ſeruant Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth, our moſt gracious Queene &amp; dread Soueraigne. Graft in her royall heart, by the working of thy holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, thy manifolde good gifts and benefites, as wiſedome, grace, perſeuerance in thy trueth, encreaſe of faith and affiance in thee: defende her
<pb facs="tcp:6948:39"/> (O Lorde) with thy mightie hand, and outſtretched arme: graunt vnto her a moſt hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, long and proſperous reigne ouer vs. Moreouer (O Lorde) if the ſeruice of golden veſſels in thy Temple at Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, were accetable vnto thee: vouchſafe this thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant to bee eſteemed in thy ſight, as a moſt honorable or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament in the new Ieruſalem, not built with money, by the labour of the ſeruants of the firſt Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but bought with the precious blood of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde Salomon thy ſonne our Sauiour. Beholde her, &amp; make
<pb facs="tcp:6948:40"/> her to be, O Lorde, as the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ſtone or ſignet of thine owne hande, and as the apple of thine eye, for thy truethes ſake: to the enemies whereof, make her name moſt dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and to thy Church where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer diſperſed, moſt accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and ioyfull. Confounde and put to ſhame, O Lord, all thoſe that wiſh or procure a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny euill to her royall perſon, or diminution of her kingdomes, and imperiall dignitie ouer them. And when for the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of our ſinnes, O Lorde, thou wilt puniſh vs with the winde of thy diſpleaſure, by
<pb facs="tcp:6948:40"/> taking from vs this our fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grant and ſweete ſmelling flower, which we beſeech thee for thine owne names ſake long to deferre: then (O Lord) plant her in the garden of thy preſence, where ſhee may growe and dwell in felicitie incomparable, which the eye hath not ſeene, the eare hath not hearde, neither euer came it into the vnderſtanding of man, thoſe ioyes which thou haſt prepared for her, and all thine elect. Moreouer (O Lorde) graunt thy heauenly wiſedome and grace vnto all vs her ſubiects, that wee may
<pb facs="tcp:6948:41"/> aduiſedly conſider, and dueti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully call to our remembrance, the manifolde bleſſings that wee ſo long time haue enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and doe preſently poſſeſſe through thy mercie by her miniſterie authoritie, and the execution of her kingly office, vnder the which wee doe not only reape, and peaceably en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioye the fruites of our labours, and other corporall commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities: but alſo (that which is more worth then all this) euen the freedome and libertie of conſcience, the preaching and hearing of thy moſt holye worde, and the adminiſtration
<pb facs="tcp:6948:41"/> and receiuing of thy holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments. For all which, and many other thy bleſſings, O Lorde, worke in vs thy grace to yeelde vnto thy diuine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie all poſſible and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall prayſes and thankeſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, that it bee not ſaide vnto vs, Are there not tenne clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed? or, Is not Englande pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued from all tyrannie, and enioy all theſe benefites? But where are nowe they retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to giue thankes? Quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken our memories therefore, (O Lorde) that wee neuer bee forgetfull of thy great good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe towardes vs, and make
<pb facs="tcp:6948:42"/> vs more &amp; more, for thy ſake, reuerently to feare her, dueti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to obey her, and faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to loue, honour and ſerue her, as our naturall louing Prince, and mother, and as the meane by whom wee receiue all theſe thy good bleſſings, that her Maieſtie perceiuing our diligence, and readineſſe to obey and ſerue her, may be the oftener put in minde to feare, honour, loue, ſerue and obey thy diuine and incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Maieſtie. Furthermore, inſpire her royall heart (O Lorde) with thy diuine grace, that as ſhee hath begun to ſet
<pb facs="tcp:6948:42"/> forth and maintaine thy ſacred trueth, ſo ſhee may zealouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and boldly encreaſe, perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere and continue in the ſame, whereby the filthineſſe &amp; na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe of Antichriſt may be more and more reuealed, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition and idolatrie more and more aboliſhed and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued, and that olde lying ſerpent, and roaring lyon Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, our auncient enemie, may be more &amp; more reſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and kept backe from his malicious purpoſe, in ſeeking to deuoure and drowne vs all in ignoraunce and ſecuritie. Graunt all this, O Lorde, to
<pb facs="tcp:6948:43"/> our great comfort, her honour and immortal fame, yea to the diſcharge of her owne conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and kingly duetie: and euermore rewarde theſe thine owne good giftes in her, O Lorde, not for the worke ſake, but for Ieſus Chriſt his ſake. And when thou ſhalt, to our great ſorowe and loſſe, but to her great ioy and profite, take her from vs, crowne her, O moſt mercifull God, with a crowne of euerlaſting glorie, and giue her the full poſſeſſion of that eternall kyngdome, purchaſed by the blood of that immaculate lambe, thine only
<pb facs="tcp:6948:43"/> ſonne our Sauiour and redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Ieſus Chriſt: to whome with thee and the holy Ghoſt, three perſons and one immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall and euerlaſting GOD, be all honour, dominion, prayſe, and thankeſgiuing, for euer and euer, AMEN.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:6948:44"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Places, &amp; ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> of holy Scripture, <hi>wherein the mindes of the</hi> godly may be occupied at the Communion, if the time giue occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</head>
            <div type="Scripture">
               <head>
                  <hi>A prophecie of Chriſt. Eſai.</hi> CHAP. LIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>1 Of Chriſt and his kingdome, whoſe worde fewe will beleeue. 6 All men are ſinners. 11 Chriſt is our righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, 12 And is dead for our ſinnes.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ho will beleeue our report? and to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is the arme of the Lorde reueiled?</p>
               <p>2 But hee ſhall grow vp be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him as a branche, and as a roote out of a drie grounde: he
<pb facs="tcp:6948:44"/> hath neither forme nor beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: when wee ſhall ſee him, there ſhall bee no forme that wee ſhoulde deſire him.</p>
               <p>3 Hee is deſpiſed and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected of men: he is a man full of ſorowes and hath experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of infirmities: we hid as it were our faces from him: he was deſpiſed and we eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med him not.</p>
               <p>4 Surely hee hath borne our infirmities, and caried our ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes: yet we did iudge him, as plagued, &amp; ſmitten of God, and humbled.</p>
               <p>5 But hee was wounded for our tranſgreſſions, he was bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb facs="tcp:6948:45"/> for our iniquities: the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifement of our peace was vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, and with his ſtripes wee are healed.</p>
               <p>6 All wee like ſheepe haue gone aſtray: wee haue turned euery one to his owne way, &amp; the Lorde hath layd vpon him the iniquitie of vs all.</p>
               <p>7 He was oppreſſed and hee was afflicted, yet did hee not open his mouth: he is brought as a ſheepe to the ſlaughter, &amp; as a ſheepe before her ſhearer is dumme, ſo hee openeth not his mouth.</p>
               <p>8 Hee was taken out from priſon, and from iudgement:
<pb facs="tcp:6948:45"/> and who ſhall declare his age? for he was cut out of the lande of the liuing: for the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion of my people was he plagued.</p>
               <p>9 And hee made his graue with the wicked, and with the riche in his death, though hee had doone no wickedneſſe, neither was any deceite in his mouth.</p>
               <p>10 Yet the Lorde woulde breake him, &amp; make him ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to infirmities: when hee ſhall make his ſoule an offring for ſinne, he ſhall ſee his ſeede and ſhall prolong his dayes, &amp; the will of the Lord ſhall proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
<pb facs="tcp:6948:46"/> in his hand.</p>
               <p>11 Hee ſhall ſee of the tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile of his ſoule, and ſhalbe ſatiſfied: by his knowledge ſhall my righteous ſeruant iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie many: for he ſhall beare their iniquities.</p>
               <p>12 Therefore wil I giue him a portion with the great, and he ſhal deuide the ſpoyle with the ſtrong, becauſe hee hath powred out his ſoule vnto death: and hee was counted with the tranſgreſſers, and hee bare the ſinne of many, and prayed for the treſpaſſers.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Scripture">
               <pb facs="tcp:6948:46"/>
               <head>COLOS. Chap. 3.</head>
               <p n="1">1 IF yee then bee riſen with Chriſt, ſeeke thoſe things which are aboue, where Chriſt ſitteth at the right hande of God.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Set your affections on thinges which are aboue, and not on thinges, which are on the earth.</p>
               <p n="3">3 For ye are dead, and your life is hid with Chriſt in God.</p>
               <p n="4">4 When Chriſt which is our life, ſhal appeare, then ſhal ye alſo appeare with him in glorie.</p>
               <p n="5">5 Mortifie therefore your members which are on the
<pb facs="tcp:6948:47"/> earth, fornication, vncleannes, the inordinate affection, euill concupiſcence, and couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe which is idolatrie.</p>
               <p n="6">6 For the which thinges ſakes the wrath of God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth on the children of diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience.</p>
               <p n="7">7 Wherein ye alſo walked once, when ye liued in them.</p>
               <p n="8">8 But nowe put ye awaye euen all theſe thinges, wrath, anger, maliciouſneſſe, curſed ſpeaking, filthie ſpeaking, out of your mouth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Scripture">
               <pb facs="tcp:6948:47"/>
               <head>GALA. Chap. 5.</head>
               <p>15 IF yee bite and deuoure one another, take heede leſt ye bee conſumed one of another.</p>
               <p>16 Then I ſay, walke in the Spirite, and ye ſhall not fulfill the luſtes of the fleſh.</p>
               <p>17 For the fleſh luſteth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Spirit, and the Spirit againſt the fleſh: and theſe are contrary one to the other, ſo that ye can not doe the ſame things that ye would.</p>
               <p>18 And if ye be led by the ſpirit, ye are not vnder the law.</p>
               <p>19 Moreouer the workes of the fleſh are manifeſt, which are adulterie, fornication, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:6948:48"/> wantonneſſe,</p>
               <p>20 Idolatrie, witchcraft, hatred, debate, emulations, wrath, contentions, ſeditions, hereſies,</p>
               <p>21 Enuie, murders, drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kennes, gluttonie, &amp; ſuch like, whereof I tell you before, as I alſo haue tolde you before, that they which doe ſuche thinges, ſhall not inherite the kingdome of God.</p>
               <p>22 But the fruite of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite is loue, ioy, peace, long ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, gentleneſſe, goodneſſe, faith,</p>
               <p>23 Meekenes, tempera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie: againſt ſuch there is no Lawe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Scripture">
               <pb facs="tcp:6948:48"/>
               <p>BLeſſed is the man whom the Lorde chuſeth and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth vnto him: he ſhal dwel in his court, and ſhalbe ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with the pleaſures of his holy Temple. <hi>Pſalme</hi> 65. 4.</p>
               <p>BLeſſed are they that are called vnto the Lambes ſupper. <hi>Reuela.</hi> 19. 9.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
